### Simon Kapitza

Quantitative & Applied Ecology Group (QAEco)
The University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC, 3010
□ +61 412 914 876 ⋈ simon.kapitza.research@gmail.com

♥ @simonecology Website GitHub

I am a global change ecologist researching interactions between socioeconomic and biophysical drivers of biodiversity change. My key strength is in interdisciplinary thinking to understand, capture and predict the impact of global transitions of the anthropocene on ecosystems, biodiversity and species.

#### Skills

Data Analysis	Proficient R user with experience in knitr, sweave, and RMarkdown, as well as integration of basic C++ via the RCpp package. Particularly experienced with very large spatial data sets and parallel processing (MaxEnt, Regression Trees, Linear Mixed Models). GitHub for version control. Intermediate experience with Python, SQL, ArcGIS, QGIS.
Leadership	Independently funded research visits and seminar talks, co-organisation and chairing of BES conference session, lead author on interdisciplinary research involving researchers from two institutes.
Languages	German ●●● English ●●● Spanish ●○○ French ●○○
Education	
2017 - present	PhD - Science University of Melbourne
	Supervisors: Prof Brendan Wintle, Dr Nick Golding Project: Global integrated assessment of biophysical and socioeconomic drivers of biodiversity change
2013 - 2016	MSc - Environmental Sciences (High Distinction), Albert-Ludwigs-Universitaet Freiburg Supervisors: Prof Carsten Dormann, Prof Brendan Wintle
	Project: Alleviating climate change uncertainty through improved modelling: Australian Great Desert Skinks under a changing fire regime (in collaboration with QAEco)
2009 - 2013	BSc Hon - Environmental Science and Politics University of Stirling
	Supervisor: Prof Daisy Dent Project: Rural Livelihoods in Changing Contexts: Causes and Impacts of Deforestation in Ta Veaeng District, Cambodia
2011 - 2012	Study Abroad University of Sydney
Presentations	
2019	Predicting fractional land-use maps  Friends of the Madingley model meeting, University of Cambridge  The economy, climate change and biodiversity  Centre of Biodiveristy and Environment Research seminar, University College London
2018	Department of Biogeography colloquium, Humboldt University of Berlin Integrating drivers of change: an assessment of bio-physical and socio-economic climate
	change impacts on species habitat
	Ecological Society of Australia Conference, Brisbane British Ecological Society Annual Meeting, Birmingham
	Accounting for socio-economic impacts in biodiversity modelling
	British Ecological Society Quantitative Ecology Spatial Interest Group conference, St. Andrews  Assessing direct and indirect impacts of climate change on bird habitat  Poster International Statistical Ecology Conference, St. Andrews
	Poster, International Statistical Ecology Conference, St. Andrews  Indirect impacts of climate change on future bird habitat in Vietnam and Australia PhD confirmation seminar, School of BioSciences, University of Melbourne
	Comparing the biophysical and economic impacts of climate change on biodiversity
2017	Visiting scholar seminar, Helmholtz Institute for Zoology and Wildlife Research, Berlin Accounting for socioeconomic drivers of biodiversity change: A novel integrated assessment framework
2016	Seminar, Quantitative & Applied Ecology Group, University of Melbourne Alleviating climate change uncertainty through improved modelling: Great Desert Skinks
	under a changing fire regime  MSc completion seminar, School of BioSciences, University of Melbourne

# Workshops

2019	CBRI Grand Challenges
	University of Melbourne Computational Biology Research Initiative
2018 Spatial Point Pattern Analysis	
	Australian Research Council Centre of Excellence for Mathematical and Statistical Frontiers
	Combining Different Data Types In a Single Model
	International Statistical Ecology Conference 2018

#### **Publications**

**Kapitza, S.**, Ha, P. V., Golding, N., Kompas, T, Cadenhead, N. C. R., Bal, P., Wintle, B.A., Assessing biophysical and socio-economic impacts of climate change on biodiversity (under review)

**Kapitza, S.**, Golding, N., Improved spatially-explicit land-use change modelling to predict future land use and biodiversity outcomes (in prep)

**Kapitza, S.**, Cadenhead, N., Wintle, B., Alleviating climate change uncertainty through improved modelling: Great Desert Skinks under a changing fire regime (in prep)

# Awards and scholarships

2019	David H Ashton Scholarship (AUD 2900)	
2018	Wiley Award for Best Poster, International Statistical Ecology Conference, St. Andrews	
	Science Abroad Travelling Scholarship, University of Melbourne (AUD 1500)	
	Financial Support for Research or Conference Travel, University of Melbourne (AUD 2000)	
	<b>Drummond Travel Award</b> (AUD 1500)	
2017	Australian Research Council Discovery top-up grant (AUD 21,000)	
	Melbourne International Research Scholarship (AUD 120,000)	
2015	DAAD PROMOS Scholarship grant (2300 EUR)	

# Academic activities

2019	BES2019 Thematic Session: Interdisciplinary model integration to better understand spatio-temporal changes in biodiversity, Co-organiser, session chair
2019 - present	Ecology and Evolution PhD Program
2019	Orygen Youth Health International Student Welfare Project Peer leader
2018 - present	Interdisciplinary PhD Program in Refugee and Forced Migration Studies
2018 - present	British Ecological Society Quantitative Ecology Special Interest Committee member
2017 - present	QAEco Diversity and Inclusion Group Committee member
2017	QAEco mentoring scheme Co-organiser
2015 - 2016	Staff-Student Consultative Committee, University of Freiburg Student rep

# Professional experience

2016 - present	Research Assistant Dr Luke Kelly and Prof Brendan Wintle (University of Melbourne)
2014 - 2015	Research Assistant Fraunhofer Institute for Solar Energy Systems
2012 - 2013	Social Media Manager Creative Stirling
2012	Intern German Embassy Colombo
2011	Intern German Agro Action e.V. Cambodia
2008 - 2009	Workshop Coordinator Youth Educational Institute Jugendbildungsstaette Juist
C'-1'	

#### Societies

British Ecological Society, Ecological Society of Australia, BUND (Friends of the Earth Germany)

#### Referees

Prof Brendan Wintle	Dr Nick Golding
MSc and PhD supervisor	PhD Supervisor
Director NESP Threatened Species Recovery Hub	Research Fellow QAEco
University of Melbourne and University of Queensland	University of Melbourne
brendan.wintle@unimelb.edu.au	nicholas.golding@unimelb.edu.au

Melbourne, June 19, 2019 Simon Kapitza